Guide to the Claudia Koonz papers, 1992-1999 UA.29.02.0267
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Claudia Koonz papers
1992-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Koonz, Claudia
UA.29.02.0267
0.5 Linear Feet
Claudia Koonz is an emeritus professor of history at Duke University, whose research has focused on Nazi Germany and on ethnic hatreds and fears. The Claudia Koonz papers include some records related to the Refugee Action Project and a proposed center for research on human security.
Biographical / Historical
Claudia Koonz is an emeritus professor of history at Duke University, whose research has focused on Nazi Germany and on ethnic hatreds and fears.
Claudia Koonz received her B.A. from the University of Wisconsin at Madison in 1962, her M.A. from Columbia University in 1964, and her Ph.D. from Rutgers University in 1969. She has taught history at College of the Holy Cross and Duke University.
Her early research focused on Nazi Germany, particularly the role of women in supporting the Nazi Party; her published works include Mothers in the Fatherland: Women, the Family and Nazi Politics (1987) and The Nazi Conscience (2003). Her more recent research examines, in her words, "the formation of ethnic fears that endow the 'us' with the conviction they have been summoned to rid the world of an evil 'them,'" including treatment and portrayal of Muslim women who wear a hijab in contemporary Europe.
During the 1990s, Claudia Koonz was involved with the Refugee Action Project (RAP, later Service Opportunities in Leadership, SOL) at Duke, a part of the Hart Leadership Program that placed students in internships with refugee relief organizations around the world. She was also invovled with efforts to create a center for research on human security.
Sources: Claudia Koonz faculty profile page on Duke History Department website, https://history.duke.edu/people/claudia-koonz, accessed 09 September 2019.
Claudia Koonz wikipedia page, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claudia_Koonz, accessed 09 September 2019.
Access Restrictions
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Claudia Koonz papers were received by the Duke University Archives as a transfer in 2019.
Related Materials
Hart Leadership Program records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The Claudia Koonz papers include some records related to the Refugee Action Project and a proposed center for research on human security. The collection includes correspondence, reports, emails, and other materials.
Conditions Governing Access
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials have not been screened for sensitive or restricted content. Staff will need to screen materials before use. Please contact Research Services for more information.
Refugees; Human security; Ethnic conflict; Koonz, Claudia
- Accession UA2019.0069, 1
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation/Bosnian Student Project, 1992 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    FERPA restricted until 2062.
  - Medical Volunteers, 1995 (Box 1)
    Administrative restriction until 2020.
  - Karen Greenberg correspondence, 1996 (Box 1)
    Administrative restriction until 2021.
  - East-West Women, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Bosnet, 1995 (Box 1)
  - IRC Memic, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mladi Most, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Email: Human Rights, 1999 (Box 1)
    Administrative restriction until 2024.
  - Facing History, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Budget Records for Common Fund, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Ethnic Conflict and Refugee Studies Proposal, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Center for Research on Human Security 1, 1997 (Box 1)
    Administrative restriction until 2022.
  - Center for Research on Human Security 2, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Center for Research on Human Security 3, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Center for Research on Human Security 4, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Oxford Refugee Studies Center, 1996 (Box 1)